<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "poem.dtd">
<book>
    <lg n="1">
        <l>WAKE! For the Sun, who scatter'd into flight</l>
        <l>The Stars before him from the Field of Night,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Drives Night along with them from Heav'n, and strikes</l>
        <l>The Sultan's Turret with a Shaft of Light.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="2">
        <l>Before the phantom of False morning died,</l>
        <l>Methought a Voice within the Tavern cried,</l>
        <l rend="indent">"When all the Temple is prepared within,</l>
        <l>"Why nods the drowsy Worshiper outside?"</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="3">
        <l>And, as the Cock crew, those who stood before</l>
        <l>The Tavern shouted--"Open then the Door!</l>
        <l rend="indent">"You know how little while we have to stay,</l>
        <l>And, once departed, may return no more."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="4">
        <l>Now the New Year reviving old Desires,</l>
        <l>The thoughtful Soul to Solitude retires,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Where the WHITE HAND OF MOSES on the Bough</l>
        <l>Puts out, and Jesus from the Ground suspires.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="5">
        <l>Iram indeed is gone with all his Rose,</l>
        <l>And Jamshyd's Sev'n-ring'd Cup where no one knows;</l>
        <l rend="indent">But still a Ruby kindles in the Vine,</l>
        <l>And many a Garden by the Water blows.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="6">
        <l>And David's lips are lockt; but in divine</l>
        <l>High-piping Pehlevi, with "Wine! Wine! Wine!</l>
        <l rend="indent">"Red Wine!"--the Nightingale cries to the Rose</l>
        <l>That sallow cheek of hers to' incarnadine.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="7">
        <l>Come, fill the Cup, and in the fire of Spring</l>
        <l>Your Winter garment of Repentance fling:</l>
        <l rend="indent">The Bird of Time has but a little way</l>
        <l>To flutter--and the Bird is on the Wing.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="8">
        <l>Whether at Naishapur or Babylon,</l>
        <l>Whether the Cup with sweet or bitter run,</l>
        <l rend="indent">The Wine of Life keeps oozing drop by drop,</l>
        <l>The Leaves of Life keep falling one by one.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="9">
        <l>Each Morn a thousand Roses brings, you say:</l>
        <l>Yes, but where leaves the Rose of Yesterday?</l>
        <l rend="indent">And this first Summer month that brings the Rose</l>
        <l>Shall take Jamshyd and Kaikobad away.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="10">
        <l>Well, let it take them! What have we to do</l>
        <l>With Kaikobad the Great, or Kaikhosru?</l>
        <l rend="indent">Let Zal and Rustum bluster as they will,</l>
        <l>Or Hatim call to Supper--heed not you.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="11">
        <l>With me along the strip of Herbage strown</l>
        <l>That just divides the desert from the sown,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Where name of Slave and Sultan is forgot--</l>
        <l>And Peace to Mahmud on his golden Throne!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="12">
        <l>A Book of Verses underneath the Bough,</l>
        <l>A Jug of Wine, a Loaf of Bread--and Thou</l>
        <l rend="indent">Beside me singing in the Wilderness--</l>
        <l>Oh, Wilderness were Paradise enow!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="13">
        <l>Some for the Glories of This World; and some</l>
        <l>Sigh for the Prophet's Paradise to come;</l>
        <l rend="indent">Ah, take the Cash, and let the Credit go,</l>
        <l>Nor heed the rumble of a distant Drum!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="14">
        <l>Look to the blowing Rose about us--"Lo,</l>
        <l>Laughing," she says, "into the world I blow,</l>
        <l rend="indent">At once the silken tassel of my Purse</l>
        <l>Tear, and its Treasure on the Garden throw."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="15">
        <l>And those who husbanded the Golden grain,</l>
        <l>And those who flung it to the winds like Rain,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Alike to no such aureate Earth are turn'd</l>
        <l>As, buried once, Men want dug up again.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="16">
        <l>The Worldly Hope men set their Hearts upon</l>
        <l>Turns Ashes--or it prospers; and anon,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Like Snow upon the Desert's dusty Face,</l>
        <l>Lighting a little hour or two--is gone.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="17">
        <l>Think, in this batter'd Caravanserai</l>
        <l>Whose Portals are alternate Night and Day,</l>
        <l rend="indent">How Sultan after Sultan with his Pomp</l>
        <l>Abode his destined Hour, and went his way.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="18">
        <l>They say the Lion and the Lizard keep</l>
        <l>The courts where Jamshyd gloried and drank deep:</l>
        <l rend="indent">And Bahram, that great Hunter--the Wild Ass</l>
        <l>Stamps o'er his Head, but cannot break his Sleep.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="19">
        <l>I sometimes think that never blows so red</l>
        <l>The Rose as where some buried Caesar bled;</l>
        <l rend="indent">That every Hyacinth the Garden wears</l>
        <l>Dropt in her Lap from some once lovely Head.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="20">
        <l>And this reviving Herb whose tender Green</l>
        <l>Fledges the River-Lip on which we lean--</l>
        <l rend="indent">Ah, lean upon it lightly! for who knows</l>
        <l>From what once lovely Lip it springs unseen!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="21">
        <l>Ah, my Beloved, fill the Cup that clears</l>
        <l>TO-DAY of past Regrets and future Fears:</l>
        <l rend="indent">To-morrow--Why, To-morrow I may be</l>
        <l>Myself with Yesterday's Sev'n thousand Years.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="22">
        <l>For some we loved, the loveliest and the best</l>
        <l>That from his Vintage rolling Time hath prest,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Have drunk their Cup a Round or two before,</l>
        <l>And one by one crept silently to rest.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="23">
        <l>And we, that now make merry in the Room</l>
        <l>They left, and Summer dresses in new bloom,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Ourselves must we beneath the Couch of Earth</l>
        <l>Descend--ourselves to make a Couch--for whom?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="24">
        <l>Ah, make the most of what we yet may spend,</l>
        <l>Before we too into the Dust descend;</l>
        <l rend="indent">Dust into Dust, and under Dust to lie,</l>
        <l>Sans Wine, sans Song, sans Singer, and--sans End!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="25">
        <l>Alike for those who for TO-DAY prepare,</l>
        <l>And those that after some TO-MORROW stare,</l>
        <l rend="indent">A Muezzin from the Tower of Darkness cries,</l>
        <l>"Fools! your Reward is neither Here nor There."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="26">
        <l>Why, all the Saints and Sages who discuss'd</l>
        <l>Of the Two Worlds so wisely--they are thrust</l>
        <l rend="indent">Like foolish Prophets forth; their Words to Scorn</l>
        <l>Are scatter'd, and their Mouths are stopt with Dust.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="27">
        <l>Myself when young did eagerly frequent</l>
        <l>Doctor and Saint, and heard great argument</l>
        <l rend="indent">About it and about: but evermore</l>
        <l>Came out by the same door where in I went.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="28">
        <l>With them the seed of Wisdom did I sow,</l>
        <l>And with mine own hand wrought to make it grow;</l>
        <l rend="indent">And this was all the Harvest that I reap'd--</l>
        <l>"I came like Water, and like Wind I go."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="29">
        <l>Into this Universe, and Why not knowing</l>
        <l>Nor Whence, like Water willy-nilly flowing;</l>
        <l rend="indent">And out of it, as Wind along the Waste,</l>
        <l>I know not Whither, willy-nilly blowing.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="30">
        <l>What, without asking, hither hurried Whence?</l>
        <l>And, without asking, Whither hurried hence!</l>
        <l rend="indent">Oh, many a Cup of this forbidden Wine</l>
        <l>Must drown the memory of that insolence!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="31">
        <l>Up from Earth's Center through the Seventh Gate</l>
        <l>I rose, and on the Throne of Saturn sate,</l>
        <l rend="indent">And many a Knot unravel'd by the Road;</l>
        <l>But not the Master-knot of Human Fate.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="32">
        <l>There was the Door to which I found no Key;</l>
        <l>There was the Veil through which I might not see:</l>
        <l rend="indent">Some little talk awhile of ME and THEE</l>
        <l>There was--and then no more of THEE and ME.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="33">
        <l>Earth could not answer; nor the Seas that mourn</l>
        <l>In flowing Purple, of their Lord Forlorn;</l>
        <l rend="indent">Nor rolling Heaven, with all his Signs reveal'd</l>
        <l>And hidden by the sleeve of Night and Morn.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="34">
        <l>Then of the THEE IN ME who works behind</l>
        <l>The Veil, I lifted up my hands to find</l>
        <l rend="indent">A lamp amid the Darkness; and I heard,</l>
        <l>As from Without--"THE ME WITHIN THEE BLIND!"</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="35">
        <l>Then to the Lip of this poor earthen Urn</l>
        <l>I lean'd, the Secret of my Life to learn:</l>
        <l rend="indent">And Lip to Lip it murmur'd--"While you live,</l>
        <l>"Drink!--for, once dead, you never shall return."</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="36">
        <l>I think the Vessel, that with fugitive</l>
        <l>Articulation answer'd, once did live,</l>
        <l rend="indent">And drink; and Ah! the passive Lip I kiss'd,</l>
        <l>How many Kisses might it take--and give!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="37">
        <l>For I remember stopping by the way</l>
        <l>To watch a Potter thumping his wet Clay:</l>
        <l rend="indent">And with its all-obliterated Tongue</l>
        <l>It murmur'd--"Gently, Brother, gently, pray!"</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="38">
        <l>And has not such a Story from of Old</l>
        <l>Down Man's successive generations roll'd</l>
        <l rend="indent">Of such a clod of saturated Earth</l>
        <l>Cast by the Maker into Human mold?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="39">
        <l>And not a drop that from our Cups we throw</l>
        <l>For Earth to drink of, but may steal below</l>
        <l rend="indent">To quench the fire of Anguish in some Eye</l>
        <l>There hidden--far beneath, and long ago.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="40">
        <l>As then the Tulip for her morning sup</l>
        <l>Of Heav'nly Vintage from the soil looks up,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Do you devoutly do the like, till Heav'n</l>
        <l>To Earth invert you--like an empty Cup.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="41">
        <l>Perplext no more with Human or Divine,</l>
        <l>To-morrow's tangle to the winds resign,</l>
        <l rend="indent">And lose your fingers in the tresses of</l>
        <l>The Cypress-slender Minister of Wine.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="42">
        <l>And if the Wine you drink, the Lip you press,</l>
        <l>End in what All begins and ends in--Yes;</l>
        <l rend="indent">Think then you are TO-DAY what YESTERDAY</l>
        <l>You were--TO-MORROW you shall not be less.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="43">
        <l>So when that Angel of the darker Drink</l>
        <l>At last shall find you by the river-brink,</l>
        <l rend="indent">And, offering his Cup, invite your Soul</l>
        <l>Forth to your Lips to quaff--you shall not shrink.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="44">
        <l>Why, if the Soul can fling the Dust aside,</l>
        <l>And naked on the Air of Heaven ride,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Were't not a Shame--were't not a Shame for him</l>
        <l>In this clay carcass crippled to abide?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="45">
        <l>'Tis but a Tent where takes his one day's rest</l>
        <l>A Sultan to the realm of Death addrest;</l>
        <l rend="indent">The Sultan rises, and the dark Ferrash</l>
        <l>Strikes, and prepares it for another Guest.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="46">
        <l>And fear not lest Existence closing your</l>
        <l>Account, and mine, should know the like no more;</l>
        <l rend="indent">The Eternal Saki from that Bowl has pour'd</l>
        <l>Millions of Bubbles like us, and will pour.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="47">
        <l>When You and I behind the Veil are past,</l>
        <l>Oh, but the long, long while the World shall last,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Which of our Coming and Departure heeds</l>
        <l>As the Sea's self should heed a pebble-cast.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="48">
        <l>A Moment's Halt--a momentary taste</l>
        <l>Of BEING from the Well amid the Waste--</l>
        <l rend="indent">And Lo!--the phantom Caravan has reach'd</l>
        <l>The NOTHING it set out from--Oh, make haste!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="49">
        <l>Would you that spangle of Existence spend</l>
        <l>About THE SECRET--quick about it, Friend!</l>
        <l rend="indent">A Hair perhaps divides the False from True--</l>
        <l>And upon what, prithee, may life depend?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="50">
        <l>A Hair perhaps divides the False and True;</l>
        <l>Yes; and a single Alif were the clue--</l>
        <l rend="indent">Could you but find it--to the Treasure-house,</l>
        <l>And peradventure to THE MASTER too;</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="51">
        <l>Whose secret Presence through Creation's veins</l>
        <l>Running Quicksilver-like eludes your pains;</l>
        <l rend="indent">Taking all shapes from Mah to Mahi and</l>
        <l>They change and perish all--but He remains;</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="52">
        <l>A moment guessed--then back behind the Fold</l>
        <l>Immerst of Darkness round the Drama roll'd</l>
        <l rend="indent">Which, for the Pastime of Eternity,</l>
        <l>He doth Himself contrive, enact, behold.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="53">
        <l>But if in vain, down on the stubborn floor</l>
        <l>Of Earth, and up to Heav'n's unopening Door,</l>
        <l rend="indent">You gaze TO-DAY, while You are You--how then</l>
        <l>TO-MORROW, when You shall be You no more?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="54">
        <l>Waste not your Hour, nor in the vain pursuit</l>
        <l>Of This and That endeavor and dispute;</l>
        <l rend="indent">Better be jocund with the fruitful Grape</l>
        <l>Than sadden after none, or bitter, Fruit.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="55">
        <l>You know, my Friends, with what a brave Carouse</l>
        <l>I made a Second Marriage in my house;</l>
        <l rend="indent">Divorced old barren Reason from my Bed,</l>
        <l>And took the Daughter of the Vine to Spouse.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="56">
        <l>For "Is" and "Is-not" though with Rule and Line</l>
        <l>And "UP-AND-DOWN" by Logic I define,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Of all that one should care to fathom, I</l>
        <l>was never deep in anything but--Wine.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="57">
        <l>Ah, by my Computations, People say,</l>
        <l>Reduce the Year to better reckoning?--Nay,</l>
        <l rend="indent">'Twas only striking from the Calendar</l>
        <l>Unborn To-morrow and dead Yesterday.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="58">
        <l>And lately, by the Tavern Door agape,</l>
        <l>Came shining through the Dusk an Angel Shape</l>
        <l rend="indent">Bearing a Vessel on his Shoulder; and</l>
        <l>He bid me taste of it; and 'twas--the Grape!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="59">
        <l>The Grape that can with Logic absolute</l>
        <l>The Two-and-Seventy jarring Sects confute:</l>
        <l rend="indent">The sovereign Alchemist that in a trice</l>
        <l>Life's leaden metal into Gold transmute;</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="60">
        <l>The mighty Mahmud, Allah-breathing Lord,</l>
        <l>That all the misbelieving and black Horde</l>
        <l rend="indent">Of Fears and Sorrows that infest the Soul</l>
        <l>Scatters before him with his whirlwind Sword.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="61">
        <l>Why, be this Juice the growth of God, who dare</l>
        <l>Blaspheme the twisted tendril as a Snare?</l>
        <l rend="indent">A Blessing, we should use it, should we not?</l>
        <l>And if a Curse--why, then, Who set it there?</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="62">
        <l>I must abjure the Balm of Life, I must,</l>
        <l>Scared by some After-reckoning ta'en on trust,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Or lured with Hope of some Diviner Drink,</l>
        <l>To fill the Cup--when crumbled into Dust!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="63">
        <l>Of threats of Hell and Hopes of Paradise!</l>
        <l>One thing at least is certain--This Life flies;</l>
        <l rend="indent">One thing is certain and the rest is Lies;</l>
        <l>The Flower that once has blown for ever dies.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="64">
        <l>Strange, is it not? that of the myriads who</l>
        <l>Before us pass'd the door of Darkness through,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Not one returns to tell us of the Road,</l>
        <l>Which to discover we must travel too.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="65">
        <l>The Revelations of Devout and Learn'd</l>
        <l>Who rose before us, and as Prophets burn'd,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Are all but Stories, which, awoke from Sleep</l>
        <l>They told their comrades, and to Sleep return'd.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="66">
        <l>I sent my Soul through the Invisible,</l>
        <l>Some letter of that After-life to spell:</l>
        <l rend="indent">And by and by my Soul return'd to me,</l>
        <l>And answer'd "I Myself am Heav'n and Hell:"</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="67">
        <l>Heav'n but the Vision of fulfill'd Desire,</l>
        <l>And Hell the Shadow from a Soul on fire,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Cast on the Darkness into which Ourselves,</l>
        <l>So late emerged from, shall so soon expire.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="68">
        <l>We are no other than a moving row</l>
        <l>Of Magic Shadow-shapes that come and go</l>
        <l rend="indent">Round with the Sun-illumined Lantern held</l>
        <l>In Midnight by the Master of the Show;</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="69">
        <l>But helpless Pieces of the Game He plays</l>
        <l>Upon this Chequer-board of Nights and Days;</l>
        <l rend="indent">Hither and thither moves, and checks, and slays,</l>
        <l>And one by one back in the Closet lays.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="70">
        <l>The Ball no question makes of Ayes and Noes,</l>
        <l>But Here or There as strikes the Player goes;</l>
        <l rend="indent">And He that toss'd you down into the Field,</l>
        <l>He knows about it all--HE knows--HE knows!</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="71">
        <l>The Moving Finger writes; and, having writ,</l>
        <l>Moves on: nor all your Piety nor Wit</l>
        <l rend="indent">Shall lure it back to cancel half a Line,</l>
        <l>Nor all your Tears wash out a Word of it.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="72">
        <l>And that inverted Bowl they call the Sky,</l>
        <l>Whereunder crawling coop'd we live and die,</l>
        <l rend="indent">Lift not your hands to It for help--for It</l>
        <l>As impotently moves as you or I.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="73">
        <l>With Earth's first Clay They did the Last Man knead,</l>
        <l>And there of the Last Harvest sow'd the Seed:</l>
        <l rend="indent">And the first Morning of Creation wrote</l>
        <l>What the Last Dawn of Reckoning shall read.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="74">
        <l>YESTERDAY This Day's Madness did prepare;</l>
        <l>TO-MORROW's Silence, Triumph, or Despair:</l>
        <l rend="indent">Drink! for you not know whence you came, nor why:</l>
        <l>Drink! for you know not why you go, nor where.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg n="75">
        <l>I tell you this--When, started from the Goal,</l>
        <l>Over the flaming shoulders of the Foal</l>
        <l rend="indent">Of Heav'n Parwin and Mushtari they flung,</l>
        <l>In my predestined Plot of Dust and Soul.</l>
    </lg>

</book>
